Taren Sanders

ACADEMIC RESEARCHER & DATA SCIENTIST

Institute for Positive Psychology and Education, Australian Catholic University

□ 0412 278 640 | ▼ Taren.Sanders@acu.edu.au | © 0000-0002-4504-6008 | © tarensanders | ♥ tarensanders

Education

Doctor of Philosophy

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2016

 Thesis: Investigating associations between neighbourhood green space and weight status: A longitudinal study of Australian children aged 4 to 13 years old.

Master of Data Science (Applied)

Adelaide University 2022

Bachelor of Health Science (Honours; First Class)

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2012

· Thesis: Measuring adolescent boys' physical activity: Bout length and the influence of accelerometer epoch length.

Bachelor of Health Science (PDHPE)

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2011

Employment History _____

Program Leader

INSTITUTE FOR POSITIVE PSYCHOLOGY AND EDUCATION, AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY

2021-Current

- · Drive the strategic direction and focus of the research program
- Support academic and professional staff, as well as higher-degree students, within the program
- · Provide input as a member of the Institute Executive Management Committee on Institute priorities, and advocate for my research program
- · Developed and implemented new project management processes, including making agile management strategies standard practice.

Deputy Program Leader

INSTITUTE FOR POSITIVE PSYCHOLOGY AND EDUCATION, AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY

2017-2023

• Supported Program Leader to manage the research program

Research Fellow

Institute for Positive Psychology and Education, Australian Catholic University

2016-Current

- Conduct original, high-impact, and translational research in the areas of health, education, and psychology.
- Oversee the development, evaluation, and management of multiple large-scale school-based research projects (e.g., iPLAY; 180 schools).
- · Conduct analyses of primary and secondary data, and provided statistical support to colleagues including statistics workshops.
- · Work with industry partners (NSW Department of Education, NSW Health, Sport Australia) to provide project updates and seek input.
- Author academic and non-academic outputs, including journal articles, grant applications, stakeholder reports, and data visualisations.
- · Mentor doctoral and honours students, including reviewing and evaluating their analyses and writing.

Research Summary _____

Publications	Citations	h-Index	Mean CNCI	Mean Impact	Funding
40	1764	22	1.7	Factor 7.8	>\$1 million

Technical Skills_____

Programming Languages

R, Python, Stata, Julia

Software Development

R PACKAGES (INCLUDING CRAN SUBMISSION), PYTHON PACKAGES

Statistical Methods

MACHINE LEARNING, MULTILEVEL MODELLING, INTERVENTION EVALUATION, META-ANALYSES

Research Methods

STUDY DESIGN, INTERVENTION DEVELOPMENT, ETHICS AND RECRUITMENT

Selected Publications

For a full list of publications see my full CV (bit.ly/TarenSanders).

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Sanders, T., Noetel, M., Parker, P., Del Pozo Cruz, B., Biddle, S., Ronto, R., Hulteen, R., Parker, R., Thomas, G., De Cocker, K., Salmon, J., Hesketh, K., Weeks, N., Arnott, H., Devine, E., Vasconcellos, R. P., Pagano, R., Sherson, J., Conigrave, J., & Lonsdale, C. (2023). An umbrella review of the benefits and risks associated with youths' interactions with electronic screens. *Nature Human Behaviour*. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-023-01712-8 | JIF: 29.9

Lubans, D. R., **Sanders, T.**, Noetel, M., Parker, P., McKay, H., Morgan, P., Salmon, J., Kirwan, M., Bennie, A., Peralta, L., Cinelli, R., Moodie, M., Hartwig, T., Boyer, J., Kennedy, S. G., Plotnikoff, R. C., Hansen, V., Vasconcellos, D., Lee, J., ... Lonsdale, C. (2022). Scale-up of the Internet-based Professional Learning to help teachers promote Activity in Youth (iPLAY) intervention: A hybrid type 3 implementation-effectiveness trial. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, *19*(1), 141. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-022-01371-4 | Citations: 2; JIF: 8.7; CNCI: 0.8

Antczak, D., Lonsdale, C., del Pozo Cruz, B., Parker, P., & **Sanders, T.** (2021). Reliability of GENEActiv accelerometers to estimate sleep, physical activity, and sedentary time in children. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 18(1), 73. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-021-01143-6 | Citations: 6; JIF: 8.7; CNCI: 0.9

Noetel, M., Griffith, S., Delaney, O., Harris, N. R., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., del Pozo Cruz, B., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Multimedia Design for Learning: An Overview of Reviews With Meta-Meta-Analysis. *Review of Educational Research*. https://doi.org/10.3102/00346543211052329 | Citations: 9; JIF: 11.2; CNCI: 1.2

Lee, J., **Sanders, T.**, Antczak, D., Parker, R., Noetel, M., Parker, P., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Influences on User Engagement in Online Professional Learning: A Narrative Synthesis and Meta-Analysis. *Review of Educational Research*, 91(4), 518–576. https://doi.org/10.3102/0034654321997918 | Citations: 11; JIF: 11.2; CNCI: 3.3

Hartwig, T. B., **Sanders, T.**, Vasconcellos, D., Noetel, M., Parker, P. D., Lubans, D. R., Andrade, S., Ávila-García, M., Bartholomew, J., Belton, S., Brooks, N. E., Bugge, A., Cavero-Redondo, I., Christiansen, L. B., Cohen, K., Coppinger, T., Dyrstad, S., Errisuriz, V., Fairclough, S., ... del Pozo Cruz, B. (2021). School-based interventions modestly increase physical activity and cardiorespiratory fitness but are least effective for youth who need them most: An individual participant pooled analysis of 20 controlled trials. *British Journal of Sports Medicine*, *55*(13), 721–729. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2020-102740 | Citations: 25; JIF: 18.4; CNCI: 2.9

Lonsdale, C., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., Noetel, M., Hartwig, T., Vasconcellos, D., Lee, J., Antczak, D., Kirwan, M., Morgan, P., Salmon, J., Moodie, M., McKay, H., Bennie, A., Plotnikoff, R. C., Cinelli, R., Greene, D., Peralta, L., Cliff, D., ... Lubans, D. R. (2021). Effect of a Scalable School-Based Intervention on Cardiorespiratory Fitness in Children: A Cluster Randomized Clinical Trial. *JAMA Pediatrics*, 175(7), 680. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics. 2021.0417 | Citations: 15; JIF: 26.1; CNCI: 3.5

Noetel, M., Griffith, S., Delaney, O., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., del Pozo Cruz, B., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Video Improves Learning in Higher Education: A Systematic Review. *Review of Educational Research*, 91(2), 204–236. https://doi.org/10.3102/0034654321990713 | Citations: 41; JIF: 11.2; CNCI: 5.3

Antczak, D., Lonsdale, C., Lee, J., Hilland, T., Duncan, M. J., del Pozo Cruz, B., Hulteen, R. M., Parker, P. D., & **Sanders, T.** (2020). Physical activity and sleep are inconsistently related in healthy children: A systematic review and meta-analysis. *Sleep Medicine Reviews*, *51*, 101278. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101278 | Citations: 26; JIF: 10.5; CNCI: 1.3

Sanders, T., Parker, P. D., del Pozo-Cruz, B., Noetel, M., & Lonsdale, C. (2019). Type of screen time moderates effects on outcomes in 4013 children: Evidence from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 16(1), 117. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-019-0881-7 | Citations: 55; JIF: 8.7; CNCI: 3.8